A Guide to the Charles F. Gillette Photographs, 1905-1970
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Charles F. Gillette Photographs, 1905-1970
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11083
There are 270 items in this collection.
This collection consists of photographs, 1905-1970 and undated, of historic gardens, buildings and estates from the files of Charles Freeman Gillette (1886-1969), a Richmond landscape architect, including homes, restoration work at Colonial Williamsburg and Monticello, churches, the Cape Henry lighthouse, cemeteries, and other structures.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles Freeman Gillette (1886-1969) was a Richmond landscape architect. A native of Wisconsin, he was born in Chippewa Falls on March 14, 1886, to Orlando Gillette (d. 1926) and Katy Melville Gillette (d. 1927). He began his apprenticeship in landscape architecture with Warren Manning (1860-1938), a Boston landscape designer, in 1909. His first assignment was at Chelmsford, the Elon Huntington Hooker estate in Greenwich, Connecticut. In 1912, he married Ellen Cogswell (1880-1967), the daughter of Fillmore and Lillian Patterson Cogswell. Some notable Gillette landscape projects in Virginia include the grounds of Richmond College (1911); Nelson House in Yorktown (1915); Kenmore (1924); Virginia House and Agecroft Hall (1927); and the Executive Mansion garden (1954). For a very fine book discussing the career of Charles F. Gillette see Genius in the Garden Charles F. Gillette & Landscape Architecture in Virginia by George C. Longest.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains photographos of Virginia homes, estates and gardens. They include snapshots of older homes and sites, chiefly in Albemarle County, Va., photographed for their historical value and containing notes on the verso commenting on the original owners,unusual architectural details, or directions to the site. There are also professional photographs of well-known Virginia buildings, many of whose gardens were designed by Gillette. In addition there are copies of photographs of historical Gloucester County homes, 1905; and the 1970 report of the Historical Richmond Foundation.
Contents List
- Albemarle County -- "Ash Lawn" n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Bellair" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Blue Ridge Farm" -- Greenwood 1937 & n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Brown's Cove" n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Castle Hill" n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Cliffside" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Edgemont" 1932 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Enniscorthy" (Coles Burying Ground) 1932 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Estouteville" n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Farmington" n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Glendower" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Hampstead" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- House at Jonson's Mill, originally Cole's Mill n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- Milton 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Monticello" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Mount Air" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Mount Pleasant" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Quandry" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- Rivanna River Viaduct n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Sherwood" 1933 (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Tallwood" n.d. (Box 1)
- Albemarle County -- "Viewmont," Joshua Fry House n.d. (Box 1)
- Augusta County -- "Folly" (Serpentine Wall) n.d. (Box 1)
- Bedford County -- "Poplar Forest" n.d. (Box 1)
- Charles City County -- "Berkeley" n.d. (Box 1)
- Charles City County -- "Shirley n.d. (Box 1)
- Charles City County -- "Westover" n.d. (Box 1)
- Charlottesville -- "Old Hotel," near railroad tracks n.d. (Box 1)
- [Charlottesville?] -- "Woodlawn" n.d. (Box 1)
- Colonial Beach -- George Washington Birthplace (Popes Creek Plantation, later "Wakefield") n.d. (Box 1)
- Fairfax County -- "Gunston Hall" n.d. (Box 1)
- Fairfax County -- "Gunston Hall" n.d. (Box 1)
- Fairfax County -- "Mt. Vernon" (Gardens_ 1935 & n.d. (Box 1)
- Fairfax County -- "Gunston Hall" n.d. (Box 1)
- Fredericksburg -- Federal Hill Summer House n.d. (Box 1)
- Fredericksburg -- James Monroe Law Office n.d. (Box 1)
- Fredericksburg -- "Kenmore" n.d. (Box 1)
- Fredericksburg -- Mary Washington House n.d. (Box 1)
- Fredericksburg -- Rising Sun Tavern n.d. (Box 1)
- Gloucester County -- Abington Church n.d. (Box 1)
- Gloucester County -- Miscellaneous Homes (Booklet) ca. 1905 (Box 1)
- Gloucester County -- Ware Church n.d. (Box 1)
- Halifax County -- "Berry Hill" n.d. (Box 1)
- Henrico County -- "Wilton" n.d. (Box 1)
- Historica Richmond Foundation Report & Portfolio of Illustrations n.d. (Box 1)
- James City County -- "Carter's Grove" n.d. (Box 1)
- Jamestown -- "Old Church Tower" n.d. (Box 1)
- Lancaster County -- Christ Church n.d. (Box 1)
- Loudon County -- "Morven Park" (Garden) n.d. (Box 1)
- Loudon County -- "Oak Hill" n.d. (Box 1)
- Loudon County -- "Oatlands" n.d. (Box 1)
- [Middlesex County?] -- "Wilton" on Pianketank n.d. (Box 1)
- Nelson County -- "Edgewood" 1932 (Box 1)
- Nelson County -- "Edgewood" (Tucker Cottage) 1932 (Box 1)
- Norfolk -- Myers House n.d. (Box 1)
- Norfolk -- St. Paul's Church n.d. (Box 1)
- Orange County -- "Barboursville" n.d. (Box 1)
- Orange County -- "Montpelier" (Gardens) n.d. (Box 1)
- [Madison County] -- "Woodberry Forest" (Garden) n.d. (Box 1)
- Prince George County -- "Upper Brandon" n.d. (Box 2)
- Princess Anne County -- Adam Thoroughgood House n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- "Agecroft Hall" 1933 (Box 2)
- Richmond -- "Battle Abbey" n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- Edgar Allan Poe House n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- The Marshall House n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- "Reveille" 1934 (Box 2)
- Richmond -- St. John's Church n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- State Capitol Building n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- "Virginia House" 1936 & n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- The Virginia Museum of Fine Arts n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- White House of the Confederacy n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond -- "Wickham-Valentine House" n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond County -- "Farnham Church" n.d. (Box 2)
- Richmond County -- "Mt. Airy" n.d. (Box 2)
- Stafford County -- Acquia Church n.d. (Box 2)
- Surry County -- "Chippokes" n.d. (Box 2)
- Surry County -- Claremont ca. 1930 (Box 2)
- Surry County -- "Eastover" n.d. (Box 2)
- Surry County -- Warren House 1935 (Box 2)
- Virginia Beach -- Cape Henry Lighthouse n.d. (Box 2)
- Westmoreland County -- "Straford" n.d. (Box 2)
- Wiliamsburg -- Bruton Parish Church n.d. (Box 2)
- Wiliamsburg (Colonial) -- Gardens n.d. (Box 2)
- Wiliamsburg (Colonial) -- St. George Tucker House n.d. (Box 2)
- Yorktown -- "York Hall" 1937 (Box 2)
- Port Tobacco, Maryland -- "Habre-de-Venture" n.d. (Box 2)
- Port Tobacco, Maryland -- "La Grange" n.d. (Box 2)
- Talbot County, Maryland -- "Wye House" n.d. (Box 2)
- Cincinnati, Ohio -- "Charles Phelps Taft House" n.d. (Box 2)
- Unidentified Homes & A Studio n.d. (Box 2)
- Identified Photographs -- Location Unknown n.d. (Box 2)
  "Belmont" (Garden)
  ["Cherthouse"?]
  John Custis Tenement
  "Marmion"
  ["Mt. Airly Dower House"?]
  "Old Powder Magazine" (1703)
  "River Edge"